<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great and weighty considerations relating to the D[uke of York] or successor of the crown humbly offer'd to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and both Houses of Parliament / by a true patriot.</title>
            <author>True patriot.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13693414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13693414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 844:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great and weighty considerations relating to the D[uke of York] or successor of the crown humbly offer'd to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty and both Houses of Parliament / by a true patriot.</title>
                  <author>True patriot.</author>
                  <author>Hunt, Thomas, 1627?-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Often erroneously ascribed to Thomas Hunt.  Hunt's pamphlet entitled "The great and weighty considerations relating to the Duke of York or successor of the crown : offered to the King and both Houses of Parliament ... 1680" was written in response to this pamphlet by a true patriot.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing; Lincoln's Inn catalogue of pamphlets, p. 272; Brit. Mus. cat. under James II, col. 35; DNB; and Wood, Athenae Oxonienses, v. 4, col. 82.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101415:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101415:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Great and Weighty CONSIDERATIONS Relating to the D, or Succeſſor of the Crown, Humbly offer'd to the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, AND <hi>Both Houſes of Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By a True Patriot.</byline>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HE is undoubtedly to be reputed the beſt Friend to his King and Countrey whom neither the Fear of any Worldly Powers can deter or hinder to ſpeak, nor the love of any Temporal advantages can induce to diſſemble the Truth; eſpecially in ſuch ſerious and weighty matters, as mainly concern the welfare both of Church and State. For, whoſoever lays aſide all the alluring Conſiderations of Self-Intereſt, and chooſes rather to expoſe himſelf to the diſpleaſure of a prevailing Faction, than ſee the Truth oppreſs'd by any feign'd pretences, though never ſo ſpecious or plauſible, he ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates by the ſincerity of his intentions, how Faithful he is to God, and how Loyal to his Prince.</p>
            <p>This plain and undoubted verity, (moſt Gracious Sovereign) encourageth me at preſent to offer unto your moſt Excellent Majeſty this my humble Addreſs, briefly compriſing ſuch Reaſons, as perſwade me ſo much to miſlike many particulars of our preſent proceedings, whereby moſt prepoſterouſly we endeavour to eſtabliſh the true Reformed Religion in this Kingdom, by overthrowing the chiefeſt Principle and Maxim thereof; which is fulln epitomiz'd in this excellent Precept, <hi>Give every one his due.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot indeed but highly extol the rare conſtancy of our Leading Men in the true Proteſtant Religion, and their fervent zeal to maintain and eſtabliſh the ſame for ever; as alſo their extraordinary care and diligence to ſuppreſs Popery, and all Fanatical Leven: But I find their Zeal doth ſo far tranſport many of them beyond the limits of Juſtice and Equity, that unleſs they ſteer their courſe more conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the Divine <hi>Cynoſura</hi> of all Humane Actions, the Word and Will of God, I am afraid we ſhall have ere long as much reaſon to blame them for the one, as praiſe them for the other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101415:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101415:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101415:3"/>To eſtabliſh firmly the true Proteſtant Religion, is undoubtedly a great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious action; but to eſtabliſh it upon the Quickſands of Humane Policy, or upon grounds repugnant to the Laws both of God and Nature, is a thing, whereof neither I, nor (I hope) any faithful Chriſtian will ever approve. Hypocrites indeed, and ſome factious Spirits of the Phanatical Leven, who make a Cloak of Religion to palliate their black Deſigns, by their ſeditious Pamphlets do daily labour to perſwade the World, that nothing can be ſo Sacred, which muſt not be ſacrific'd to their pretended Religion. And upon this ground as the Rump-Parliament has Sacrific'd the beſt of Kings ſo ſome fiery Zealots now endeavour to Sacrifice the beſt of Princes, your Majeſties onely Brother. But the beſt and moſt conſcientious Proteſtants do utterly abhor and deteſt ſuch Antichriſtian attempts, as being wholly repugnant to the Ordnance of God, and to the fundamental Laws of this Kingdom. Neither did they ever approve of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archical Bill lately fram'd by ſome turbulent Zealots of the Houſe of Commons againſt his Royal Highneſs, wherein they peremptorily aſſume to themſelves a Sovereign and Deſpotical Power of Depoſing Princes, and diſpoſing of Kingdoms, as their ſpirit moves them; and withal moſt impudently affirm, that this has been the ancient cuſtom of Parliaments: Whereas it's evident to all the World, that the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> has always been Hereditary, and never depending on the Votes or Suffrages of the Subject.</p>
            <p>Nay, it is undeniable that the ſucceſſion of the Crown was always hitherto held ſo Sacred and inviolable, that no Crime whatſoever, no attainder of Treaſon could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar the next Heir of Blood from ſucceeding in the Government, as <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>page</hi> 16. teſtifieth in theſe words: <hi>If the right Heir of the Crown be attainted of Treaſon, yet the Crown ſhall deſcend to him,</hi> &amp; eo inſtante <hi>(without any other reverſal) the attainder is utterly avoided, as it fell out in the Caſe of</hi> Henry <hi>the Seventh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe cunning Politicians now will have a new model of Government; that ſo all the world may acknowledge our Omnipotent Parliament, (<hi>i e.</hi> themſelves,) to have an Abſolute and Independent power, not only over mean Subjects, but alſo over the Royal Family; nay, over the King himſelf, and to have power to degrade or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, as they pleaſe. For they are ſure, that by whatſoever Law, Power, or pretence, the Parliament can diſ-inherit or depoſe the Heir, by the ſame they may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe depoſe the Poſſeſſor of the Crown; as the Rump Parliament, <hi>de facto,</hi> has done.</p>
            <p>To what purpoſe then ſhould any true Proteſtant, or any man of ſenſe, that loves either King or Country, approve of ſuch an extravagant Bill; which Gilded over, like poiſoned Pills, with the ſpecious pretence of eſtabliſhing the true Proteſtant Religion, is like to deſtroy the very root and life of our Government? Or, what (in Gods name) do we mean by this pretence of Religion? Do we intend to out-reach the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, or do we deſpair either of the juſtneſs of our cauſe, or of the goodneſs of God? Do not we remember how the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>that evil is not to be done, that good may come of it?</hi> Or do not we know, that whatſoever God affects in goodneſs, he doth effect by good means, and doth not want our wickedneſs to fulfil his holy will? Is there no other way of eſtabliſhing the true Proteſtant Religion, but by robbing thoſe we ſhould honour and obey, and depriving them of that, which God and Nature has beſtowed upon them; I mean their Birthright? Far be it from the heart of a Chriſtian, eſpecially a Proteſtant, to think ſo ill of the all-ſeeing Providence of the Almighty. For, what is this, but exactly to follow the footſteps of that monſter of ingratitude, the wicked <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who after God of his infinite goodneſs had raiſed him from nothing, and eſtabliſhed him Monarch of the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet was he ſo miſtruſtful of Gods power in preſerving his Kingdom for the future, that he thought nothing could ſecure it but his own accurſed Policy? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.26, 27. Was not the true Proteſtant Religion ſettled in this Nation by the ſame mighty hand of God, that eſtabliſhed <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Shall we then like that wicked King, ſo far deſpair of Gods Providence in preſerving the work of his own hands, as never to think it ſecure, unleſs it be eſtabliſh'd upon the quick-ſands of our own wicked inventions? Should not we rather be terrified at that dreadful woe pronounced by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Woe unto him that buildeth his houſe by unrighteouſneſs, or his Chambers by wrong,</hi> Jer. 22.13. <hi>O inſenſati Galatae</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.) O fooliſh and timerous Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould be of ſo little Faith, as to believe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101415:3"/>
that a king of <hi>England,</hi> though the moſt zealous of Papiſts, can ever ſubvert the true Proteſtant Religion, or the preſent Government of this Kingdom, while we know him ſo far engaged by the fundamental Laws of the Land, that he can hardl move or ſtir, but with a concentrick motion to both Houſes of Parliament? Eſpecially, while we daily ſee, how in our very neighbourhood, (to omit <hi>Germany, Poland,</hi> and other places) the <hi>French</hi> Kings ever ſince the Reformation, have been moſt zealous Papiſts, and withall the moſt abſolute and arbitrary Soveraigns of all Chriſtian Monarchs; and yet all this while could not ſuppreſs the Reformed Religion there, nor hinder the over-ruling Providence of the Almighty, who has even in that Kingdom, notwithſtanding all Popiſh oppoſers, preſerved to himſelf a Remnant, not of ſeven (as he ſpeaks of the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) but of ſeventy, or rather ſeven hundred thouſand, that bow'd not the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> that is, ſubmitted not to the intolerable yoke of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Traditions? And if Gods over-ruling Providence has ſo far prevailed in protecting his people at the very dawning of the Reformation, and in cauſing Papiſts themſelves become Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, notwithſtanding all the Cruel Laws then in force againſt them, and all the oppoſition of a Popiſh; nay, of a moſt Abſolute and Arbitrary Soveraign, who might <hi>ad libitum,</hi> make ſeverer Laws againſt them and their Doctrine: Shall we of little faith, be ſo miſtruſtful of his goodneſs, now in the very Meridian of the Goſpel, as to believe that a King of <hi>England,</hi> (a King ſo far obliged by the fundamental Laws of his Kingdom, and by all tyes imaginable, to be adviſed in all weighty matters by a free Repreſentative of the whole Nation, that without this Repreſentative he can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repeal the Penal Statutes enacted againſt Papiſts, nor yet enact any, though he would, againſt the Proteſtant Religion) ſhall we, I ſay, believe that ſuch a King, and in ſuch Circumſtances, though never ſo zealous a Papiſt, can induce or perſwade his Subjects, who once received the full light and liberty of the Goſpel, ever to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Yoke of Popiſh Superſtitions?</p>
            <p>Do not we remember, how in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time, the Proteſtant Religion was in a manner in its Infancy in this Kingdom, and yet how miraculouſly it was preſerved, notwithſtanding all the endeavours of that active Queen, and all the Penal Laws then in force againſt it: And now being in its prime, and ſo firmly eſtabliſhed and fenced by Law, ſhall we deſpair of Gods power to preſerve it, unleſs we help him out with our wickedneſs? Certainly we muſt either believe the whole Nation is inclined to Popery, or the Proteſtant Religion is grounded on very weak Foundations, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we cannot thus think it impoſſible, either to ſecure our Faith and Liberties ſo well eſtabliſhed by Law, or keep off the Tyranny of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> from ſtealing upon us, under a Popiſh Succeſſor, who can neither make any new Statutes in favour of Popery, nor yet alter the preſent Government, without the conſent of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>It is an unwarrantable attempt, and a point without Example or Preſident, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherit or depoſe a Prince for not complying with his People in Religion: Neither can our ſeditious Pamphleters moſt impertinent Examples any thing juſtifie ſuch violent proceedings. They alledge, that King <hi>Aſa</hi> remov'd his Mother <hi>Maachah</hi> from being Queen, becauſe of her Idolatry, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. But they might as well juſtifie <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Tyrannical Uſurpation, by alledging the example of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> rebelling againſt <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and <hi>Jehu</hi> againſt <hi>Jöràm;</hi> for theſe Rebellions have no leſs, if not more, approbation of God's Oracles, (1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.31. and 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.6.) than <hi>Aſa</hi>'s depoſing his Mother. Such things therefore are recorded in holy Scripture to be read, but never to be imitated, (as we are not to kill our ſelves in imitation of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon,</hi> though after his death he is highly commended and by the Apoſtle reckon'd among the Faithful, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.32.) unleſs we have as plain a Revelation from God to do them, as King <hi>Aſa</hi> had to depoſe his Mother by the advice of <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prophet.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they alledge, that the people of <hi>France</hi> rejected the King of <hi>Navarr,</hi> becauſe of his Religion: But ſurely, they are either altogether ignorant, or wholly beſotted and blinded, that make uſe of this example: For, (to omit that a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Papiſts, and thoſe too of the beſt and greateſt Families of all <hi>France,</hi> then cloſly adhered to the King of <hi>Navarr,</hi> and thought themſelves indiſpenſably obliged in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by the Law of Nature and the Principles of their Religion, ſo to do, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101415:4"/>the Kings being of a different perſwaſion, and all the Popes roaring Bulls and thundring Excommunicatios to the contrary, as the beſt Hiſtorians of them times do ſufficiently teſtify) to omit, I ſay, this conſideration, which ſhould make us emulous at leaſt of theſe Papiſts Loyalty: Do not all Proteſtants generally exclaim againſt thoſe other rebellious Papiſts, who then oppoſed that worthy Prince? With what face then can we produce it as a preſident to juſtify our own proceedings againſt his Royal Highneſs? Or ſhall we judge it Antichriſtian and unlawful in Papiſts to depoſe a Prince, but lawful and Chriſtian in Proteſtants? O blind zeal! let us not thus fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceive our ſelves, but rather ſeriouſly conſider that dreadful ſentence of the Apoſtle; <hi>Thinkeſt thou, O man, that judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame thy ſelf, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God?</hi> Rom. 2.3. How do we think to eſcape the ſeverity of Gods anger and his juſt judgment, if we condemn and deteſt the Romiſh uſurpation over Kings and Princes, and yet uſe the ſame ourſelves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt remorſe of Conſcience?</p>
            <p>But the Pamphleters blindneſs is yet more remarkable, when they ridiculouſly heap together, in the very front of their Sophiſtical and moſt unreaſonable reaſons, how ſuch and ſuch Princes have been either diſinherited, baniſhed, or put to death, whether by their own rebellious Subjects, or by other encroaching Princes; as <hi>Edgar Atheling</hi> was baniſhed by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>Arthur Plantagenet</hi> put to death by King <hi>John,</hi> and the like: But the ſilly Sophiſters never endeavoured, nor ever could juſtify theſe examples, or prove them either lawful or laudable. To what purpoſe then are ſuch unjuſtifyable preſidents produced by theſe factious Spirits, to warrant their own deſperate attempts? Surely, they might as well argue that Chriſt was crucified by the Jews, and thence infer that Subjects might lawfully crucifie or put to death their Soveraign, when and how they pleaſed. But ſuch Antichriſtian and Fanatical Logick was never heard, much leſs approved of, until the Spirit of <hi>Belial</hi> reveal'd it to <hi>Oliver</hi> and his Rumpers</p>
            <p>For if we look back to the Primitive Church, whoſe practice ſhould be a rule to our proceedings, though they were zealous to admiration of the true Faith and Worſhip of God, (<hi>having the firſt fruits of the Spirit,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23.) and though their Soveraigns for many hundred years were either downright Idolaters, or blaſphemous Hereticks, and withall moſt Cruel Perſecutors of Chriſts Church, yet in all this time we cannot find one Prince diſinherited or depoſed by his Chriſtian Subjects, for being of a contrary profeſſion, no, nor yet for his Tyrannical Perſecutions: For they well knew how God commanded them, <hi>To ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> (1 Pet. 2.13. and to obey higher powers, (though Heathens, as then they were) <hi>beauſe there is no power but of God,</hi> (Rom. 13.1.) <hi>By whom Kings do reign and Princes decree juſtice,</hi> Prov. 8.15. True Chriſtians were numerous in the days of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> Emperors, and yet they never attempted to diſ-inherit or depoſe theſe Princes, notwithſtanding their Blaſphemous Hereſies. Many Chriſtians well knew how <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, notwithſtanding his external pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity, was a Heathen in his heart, long before he came to the Empire; and yet they never endeavoured to deprive him of his Birth-right, but left all to the providence of God, whom they aſſuredly knew alwayes potent, and willing to protect his own inheritance, <hi>the Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to come nearer home, when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of glorious memory, came to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> the Proteſtants of this Kingdom were but a handful in reſpect of the Papiſts, and though the Queen was already declared Illegitimate even by her own Father, and this confirmed by an Act of Parliament, yet the Papiſts endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured not to depoſe or debar her from her Right for being of a contrary Religion, but publickly own'd her as their true and lawful Sovereign. Shall we then ſhew our ſelves worſe than the Papiſts, or more miſtruſtful of God's mercy? Is it not evident, that our ſins are the cauſe why your Majeſty hath no lawful Iſſue? Should not we then rather remove the cauſe by our ſerious repentance, than prepoſterouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to mend the matter, by adding fuel to the flame, heaping one ſin upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in robbing others of that which God and Nature has beſtowed upon them? Surely 'tis a <hi>Motto</hi> better beſeeming a Chriſtian, <hi>Ruat Coelum, &amp; fiat Juſtitia,</hi> than, <hi>Faciamus mala ut eveniant bona.</hi> And it is the beſt Religion that gives every one his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101415:4"/>
due, not that which cannot ſubſiſt without depriving others of their undoubted Right.</p>
            <p>But what do we intend to do, or ſhall we ſhake off all Conſcience, and neither regard our Loyalty to our Prince, nor yet our Oathes to God? Do not we remember, how in taking the Oath of Allegiance, we have called God to teſtifie our candour and ſincerity in pronouncing the enſuing words, <hi>I do ſwear from my heart, that — I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſo-ever, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Crown and Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> — With what conſcience then can we ſubſcribe or conſent to that unadviſed Bill, fram'd by ſome Members of the Houſe of Commons againſt his Royal Highneſs, after ſwearing ſo poſitively to bear Faith and true Allegiance, not only to your Majeſty, but alſo to your Heirs and Succeſſors; nay, to defend them to the uttermoſt of our power againſt all attempts whatſoever, and ſwearing this with a <hi>Non-obſtante</hi> to any Sentence or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, whether from the Pope or otherwiſe. For ſurely, the word <hi>[otherwiſe]</hi> excludes all other Sententences and Declarations, as well as the Popes; and conſequently no leſs excludes this ill-digeſted Bill of the Houſe of Commons, than the roaring Bulls of the See of <hi>Rome:</hi> For (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) <hi>Nihil excipitur, ubi diſtinguitur nihil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! but our great Politicians have ſound out a new Comment upon theſe words; for, in effect, they tell us, that by Heirs here, we are to underſtand thoſe that are created ſuch, not by God, but by the Parliament: And that although by Birth one might claim a right to ſucceed in the Government, yet when the Parliament declares to the contrary, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulls this Claim, he is no longer Heir to the Crown, and conſequently the People are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from their Oath of Allegiance to him. A <hi>Commentum</hi> indeed, and a Diabolical Fiction, nay, the worſt of all Jeſuitical Equivocations: In the ſame Oath we call God to witneſs, that we ſwear in the plain and common ſenſe of the words, without any Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, Mental Reſervation, or ſecret Evaſion whatſoever. And after ſwearing in this manner, how dare we make uſe of this ſo palpable an Equivocation, and ſecret Evaſion, which, if practiſed, ſhould render all Oathes vain and ineffectual, and this purpoſely to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour our own perfidious and perjurious dealings? We cannot deny, but that by Heir, in the plain and vulgar, or common ſenſe of the Word, we underſtand ſuch as by Blood (for Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is not uſual amongſt us) have greateſt right to ſucceed next in the Inheritance, or to poſſeſs the ſame. How then can we; without groſly equivocating, interpret it of Heirs made by Act of Parliament, at leaſt while the Natural Heir is alive, when we know it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Maxim of the Law, <hi>Solus Deus Haeredem facere potest, non homo?</hi> Do not we ſee, that the worſt of Jeſuits could at this rate take the Oath of Allegiance, and gloſſing it after this new mode, underſtand by your Majeſties Heirs and Succeſſors, thoſe that ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſuch, not by King and Parliament, but by the Pope and See of <hi>Rome?</hi> Nay, could not he further alledge, in our Grand <hi>Machivilians</hi> new Dialect, that although a King of <hi>England</hi> had right till then to Rule and Govern the Kingdom, yet when the Pope declares to the contrary, and annuls this Right, he is no longer lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the People are, <hi>eo ipſo,</hi> abſolved from their Oath of Allegiance to him? What can our cunning Politicians alledge againſt this, or can they ſhew where the diſparity lies, ſince 'tis undeniable, that the Words of the Oath can as well bear this Jeſuitical Comment, as their own new-found Gloſſes? How then dare they deny the one, and uſe the other?</p>
            <p>Moreover, this at leaſt muſt be granted: Whoſoever is by Blood next Heir to the Crown, we are by our Oath obliged before God to bear him Faith and true Allegiance, nay, to defend him againſt all attempts, until he is diſ-inherited by Act of Parliament. Whatſoever therefore we do againſt him before this Act be fully eſtabliſhed, is a violation of our Oath. And ſince it is manifeſt, that this unnatural and abortive <hi>Embrio,</hi> unluckily hatch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by ſome over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active members of the Houſe of Commons, is directly againſt him, who by Blood is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the next Heir to the Imperial Crown of <hi>England;</hi> it neceſſarily enſueth, that the very attempt of Voting and paſſing this unparallelled Bill, makes the Actors and Abberters thereof perjurers before God and the World.</p>
            <p>To this perhaps our grand Politicians will anſwer, that the Duke is not Heir, but onely Heir Apparent, to the Crown, becauſe (as <hi>Coke</hi> obſerved) <hi>none is Heir before the death of his Anceſtor, but only Heir Apparent,</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> p. 8. And hence in their new Machiavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Logick will inforce, that to diſ-inherit his Royal Highneſs, is not againſt the Oath of Allegiance, which ſpeaketh only of Heirs, not of Heirs Apparent.</p>
            <p>A ridiculous ſhift, and a moſt ſilly evaſion; firſt, becauſe we profeſs to take the Oath, not in any by-ſenſe of the Law, but in the plain and common ſenſe of the words, as all men do uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally underſtand them: Wherefore although the Law, by Heirs, had underſtood ſuch as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to their deceaſed Anceſtors, yet fince this is not the plain and common ſenſe of the word,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101415:5"/>
and men do not generally underſtand it ſo, it can never excuſe us from a perjurious violation of our Oath. 2dly. Becauſe, by <hi>Cokes</hi> leave, this his obſervation is moſt fallacious and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent: For it is a manifeſt contradiction for one to be Heir Apparent, and not be Heir, as it is, to be a Learned man, and to be no man; it being an undoubted maxime, <hi>Prius eſt eſſe, quam eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alc.</hi> And the fallacy conſiſts herein, that the word Heir, in its full and proper notion ſignifies either an Heir Apparent, who is ſuch during the life of his Anceſtor, of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heir by right actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally inheriting, which always preſuppoſeth his Anceſtors death, or at leaſt his reſignation: But <hi>Coke</hi> moſt improperly reſtrains it to the latter, contrary to the common and uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeaking, not only of moſt men in general, but of God himſelf in his holy Scriptures, where Heirs Apparent are abſolutely and moſt commonly called Heirs; as appeareth <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.3. and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.7 <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.38. <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Luk</hi> 20.14. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>Since therefore it appeareth by ſo many paſſages of holy Scripture, that the word, Heir, in its plain and common ſenſe ſignifieth an Heir Apparent, and that we profeſs before God and the World, to take the Oath of Allegiance in the plain and common ſenſe of the words, upon what grounds can we underſtand here an Heir actually inheriting, more than an Heir Apparent? Nay, ſince the words of the Oath do ſignify as well an Heir Apparent, as an Heir actually inheriting, what a Sophiſtical Equivocation it is, to underſtand it of the one, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively of the ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er? Surely, it is no better, than if a Jeſuit had Sworn before a Magiſtrate to be true and Loyal to the Government of this Kingdom, he in the interim meaning the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not of the King or Parliament, but of his own Jeſuitical Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>Let us not therefore flatter our ſelves, or fooliſhly think that after ſo ſolemn an Oath, either, or both Houſes of Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iament can authorize us before God to deprive our Prince of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right. And truely, I admire, if they, who ſo much inſiſt upon the liberties of free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, will ever acknowledge the Parliament, or any perſon whatſoever, to have this arbitrary and deſpotical power, whereby the Axe is laid to the very root of their greateſt privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. For if it be lawful for a prevailing faction in Parliament to deprive their Prince of his undoubted Birthright, how can mean Subjects have any ſecurity either of property or liberty?</p>
            <p>And beſides, ſince it is an undoubted maxime in Moral Affairs, <hi>Illud tantum poſſumus, quod de jure poſſumus;</hi> and (as St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quod non poteſt juſte, non poteſt juſtus:</hi> Upon what grounds ſhould the Houſe of Commons, nay the whole Parliament, Claim this abſolute power, I cannot find. For its evident, that both Houſes can challenge no other authority, but what they derive from their Soveraign, and the diffuſive body of the Subjects, whom they repreſent: And no leſs manifeſt it is, that no King of <hi>England</hi> hitherto did (nor, in my Opinion, could) give his Parliament any power to depoſe or diſ-inherit himſelf, or his Heir Apparent. And if your Majeſty intends to grant them any ſuch thing at preſent, (which, I hope, your Princely wiſdom will never do) I remember your Royal Father gave the long Parliament greater power than he was aware of, which they ſoon after uſed, or rather abuſed, againſt himſelf, his Crown and Dignity. And therefore I ſay, <hi>Foelix quem faciunt paterna pericula cautum.</hi> As for the diffuſive Body of the Subjects, 'tis clear, they neither would nor could grant the Parliament this extravagant Juriſdiction: Firſt, they would not do it; for who can be ſo credulous as to believe, that any man ſo deſirous of his liberty as <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ever have been, would grant the Parliament this Deſpotical power, uncontroulably to diſpoſe of his own, much leſs of his Princes Life or Eſtate. Secondly, How could the Subjects grant the Parliament any power to deprive their Prince of his Birth-right, againſt all the Laws of God and Nature, ſince of God alone, and not of the Subjects, the Prince deriveth his whole Right and Authority? <hi>For there is no power but of God, Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>By wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Kings do Reign, and Princes decree justice, Prov.</hi> 8.15. How then can the People deprive their Prince of that, which they have no power to give? As for my own particular, I muſt confeſs, I could never underſtand, that the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> was diſpoſable by Act of Parliament; I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought the Liberties of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects to be grounded on ſurer Principles, and that no power in this Kingdom could lawfully deprive us of our Priviledges, or enthrall us to any ſervitude; whereas it's evident, that if an Act of Parliament can thus transfer the Crown upon whom they pleaſe, we can have no ſecurity, and may, according to ſuch Maxims, firſt or laſt be brought under the Tyranny of the <hi>French</hi> King, or any other Forreign Prince, if ever the corruption or mercinarineſs of a Parliament ſhould induce them to comply with a King, that ſhould have a mind to ſell the Succeſſion of the Crown to a Foreigner, upon the ſecurity of an Act of Parliament; which, according to the Tenets of theſe Politicians, can give a juſt Title.</p>
            <p>But if we conſult God's Divine Oracles, the Holy Scriptures, which undoubtedly ſhould be the chief Rule of all Humane actions, we ſhall never find any Example or Preſident to warrant theſe unparallel'd proceedings againſt his Royal Highneſs, but may find ſeveral paſſages clearly againſt it? There we find how King <hi>Ahab,</hi> though abſolute Monarch of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101415:5"/>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and conſequently needed no Parliament, but had himſelf alone as much power and authority over the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as your Majeſty and Parliament together can claim, <hi>de jure,</hi> over the Natives of <hi>England,</hi> and though this Monarch paſſionately coveted his Subject <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard, and was of himſelf little inclined to Juſtice, yet he knew, that by the Laws of God and Nature it was altogether unlawful for him to deprive <hi>Naboth</hi> of his Vineyard; but if he could not deprive him of a ſmall Vineyard, ſurely he could not rob him of his Birth-right and whole Eſtate: And if ſuch an abſolute Monarch could not do this to a mean Subject, by what colour of Juſtice can the Houſe of Commons, nay, the whole Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do it to their undoubted Prince?</p>
            <p>Certainly, if God was ſo much incenſed againſt <hi>Eſau</hi> for ſelling his Birth right to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. how much (think we) ſhall his fury be kindled againſt our proceedings, where not an ordinary man, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> looſeth his Birth-right, but a moſt illuſtrious Prince, by Birth and Lineal Deſcent of ſo many Glorious Kings; and looſeth not a Birth-right to a ſmall Inheritance, but to ſeveral Kingdoms; and that not made away by himſelf, but contrary to his will and all juſtice is robb'd thereof by a prevailing Faction of his Inferiours?</p>
            <p>But if neither the unlawfulneſs of this deſperate attempt, nor the heinous guilt of perjury thereupon neceſſarily enſuing, can move or deter us from it, yet let both our private and publick dangers, and the ſad effects inevitably conſequential thereunto, withdraw us from ſuch violent proceedings. If it be God's pleaſure, that his Royal Highneſs ſhall ſurvive your Sacred Majeſty, without having any Lawful Iſſue, we need not doubt, but he will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to recover his Right by force, if by fair means he cannot. And in this caſe we may conſider, how theſe three Kingdoms are moſt ſtrangely divided into a numberleſs number both of Religions and Intereſts; and it is a true ſaying, <hi>Omne Regnum in ſe diviſum deſolabitur.</hi> And the ſtrength of Proteſtants abroad is not very great, and their will to help us, if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, I am afraid is leſs. But the Papiſts are very ſtrong, and we may be ſure the Pope will prevail with moſt of them to help a Catholick Prince, deprived of his Right for his Religion; and, no doubt, will not be backward himſelf in the Expedition. The <hi>French</hi> King likewiſe (who is now in a manner at peace with all the World, and yet muſt of neceſſity be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in action, to give vent to the fiery Spirits of his buſie Subjects) will undoubtedly be glad of the opportunity, and will hold it a glorious pretence to aſſiſt (though, I am afraid, moſt for his own ends) a Catholick Prince, excluded from his Kingdom for the Catholick Faith. And without all peradventure, his Royal Highneſs ſhall find enough even in theſe three Kingdoms, not onely of Papiſts, and other Male-contents, but alſo of the beſt and moſt conſcientious Proteſtants, as in duty bound, ready to take his part in ſo juſt a quarrel.</p>
            <p>How then ſhall we defend our ſelves, neither united at home, nor aſſiſted from abroad? or ſhall we expect to be miraculouſly delivered by God, of whoſe protection and providence we ſhew our ſelves now ſo miſtruſtful? Truely, I am afraid, we ſhall rather be miraculouſly puniſhed (like <hi>Sodom</hi> or <hi>Gomorrah</hi>) for our hainous ſins and daily multiplyed tranſgreſſions, than any wayes delivered from the juſt judgments of God, unleſs we refrain in time from our deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate proceedings, and no more endeavour with ſuch manifeſt injuſtice to hinder the order of Gods Providence, or debar our Prince, becauſe of a different perſwaſion, from his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Birthright. For nothing doth ſo much exaſperate the divine patience and longani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as to eſtabliſh injuſtice by publick authority, and to make that ſeem lawful, which the Law of God declares abominable. By what means then can we expect to eſcape his vengeance, if the great Repreſentative of the whole Nation, which ſhould reform and redreſs all tranſgreſſions of Gods Law, do attempt, contrary to the expreſs word of God and all juſtice, to rob their Prince of his undoubted right, and to make the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> which ſince the beginning of Monarchy in this Iſland, was never got but by Conqueſt or Inheritance, now to go by Election, and the greateſt Vote in the Houſe of Commons; thereby making the King himſelf for all enſuing Ages to be Tenant at will to every prevailing Faction in Parliament? I ſay, Tenant at will; for nothing is more certain, than that by whatſoever power or pretence the Parliament can depoſe the preſumptive Heir, by the ſame they may depoſe the actual poſſeſſor of the Crown; as the Rump Parliament well underſtood. For the fundamental Reaſon, why a preſumptive Heir to the Crown may be dis-inherited or depoſed either by King, Parliament, or both together, is, becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſuſpected to tend to the Subverſion of the Government, or of the true Religion here eſtabliſhed by Law, is neceſſarily to be removed, to ſecure the good and welfare of the people, according to the Ancient ſaying: <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex eſto.</hi> But that this reaſon has no leſs force againſt the Actual Poſſeſſor, than againſt the Preſumptive Heir, of the Crown, is a thing in it ſelf ſo evident, that I think no man in his wits, eſpecially acquainted with the late inteſtine troubles and preſent temper of our blind Zealots, can call it into queſtion.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101415:6"/>
For, what, if the King himſelf be at any time thus ſuſpected to endeavour the Subverſion of the Government, is there no remedy to be expected? Undoubtly their is, ſay our great Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and a good one too: For, our Omnipotent Parliament, (<hi>i. e.</hi> themſelves only and their Emiſſaries, whoſe Religion is the Bellowes of Rebellion) the grand Jury of the whole Nation, and the publick Inqueſt of all Grievances, is authorized by God (when the King fails) to uſe their abſolute Power againſt all manner of perſons, of what degree, or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever they be, to ſecure the good and welfare of the people, becauſe (as before ſaid) <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex eſto.</hi> And thus our grand Principle, as it is the fundamental Reaſon of depoſing a preſumptive Heir to the Crown, ſo it is the ground work of all Anarchy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: It is the ſpring and ſource of all our laſt inteſtine troubles, which overflow'd the three Kingdoms with a deluge of crimſon ſtreames; nay, it was the chief foundation, whereon the bloody Rumpers chiefly inſiſted in Sacrificing our Royal Martyr, as a Tyrant Subverting the Government and true Proteſtant Religion. But if a Prince ſo mild, ſo juſt, and ſo Religious, be thus Cruelly Butcher'd upon theſe grounds by a prevailing Faction of his Subjects, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable to me, how can any King of <hi>England</hi> judge himſelf otherwiſe than Tenant at will to every prevailing Faction in Parliament, or at leaſt think himſelf ſecure, while ſuch principles are maintained by his Subjects; eſpecially if they be eſtabliſhed by Law, as in effect they would have been, had that abortive Embrio of the Houſe of Commons received life (which I hope will never happen) through the influence of Your Majeſties Royal Aſſent.</p>
            <p>Truly, our greateſt comfort in this deſperate juncture of Affairs, after the unlimitted mercy of our gracious Saviour, is, the aſſured confidence we always repoſe in Your Majeſties Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom and Courage, and in the Grave and Mature Deliberations of the Houſe of Lords, and of Your moſt Honourable Privy-Council; whoſe tryed Loyalty both to Your Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to Your Royal Father, aſſures us, that neither the pretence of eſtabliſhing the true Proteſtat Religion, (which of it ſelf is ſufficiently upheld by the mighty hand of God) nor any conſideration of Temporal gain or Worldly intereſt, can induce them to decline in the leaſt from their Sworn Allegiance and Fidelity to the Royal Blood of your Glorious Father, who ſo magnanimouſly depoſed his life in defence of his Subjects Lives and Liberties, againſt the Anarchial encroachments of the Factious Members of the Houſe of Commons in the Rump Parliament; whoſe footſteps ſome (I am afraid) no leſs Factious Members of this preſent Houſe of Commons ſeem exactly to follow; pretending, as the former did, to ſecure and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the true Proteſtant Religion, according to that <hi>Machiavilian</hi> maxime, <hi>Quoties vis fallere plebem, finge Deum:</hi> Whereas it is apparent, they do no more regard the eſtabliſhing thereof, than the Rump Parliament did in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s dayes.</p>
            <p>Yet this I ſay not (no, nor any thing elſe I have hitherto miſliked or reprehended) of the whole Houſe of Commons, much leſs of the whole Parliament: God forbid, I ſhould think ſo ill of that Grave and Reverend Senate. I know there are many true and well-meaning Loyaliſts in that Honourable Houſe, who bear the Faith and Allegiance, as well as the name and power of the Commons of <hi>England.</hi> And I am of Opinion, that as the Faithful and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhops at the Councel of <hi>Arimine,</hi> through their over zealous deſire of procuring the peace and unity of Chriſts Church, were by the ſpecious Arguments of the <hi>Arians</hi> inclined unawares to make a decree againſt the true Faith and Doctrine of Chriſt; which unadviſed decree, themſelves upon ſecond thoughts and more mature deliberations, ſeeing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected advantages their Adverſaries took by their well intended condeſcenſion, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recalled, and publickly proteſted againſt it: So theſe Loyal and well meaning Members of the Houſe of Commons, through their exceſſive zeal of eſtabliſhing the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, were by the plauſible pretences of ſome overactive Spirits, induced unwittingly to Vote againſt that Allegiance and Fidelity they Swore not only to your Majeſty, but alſo to your Heirs and Succeſſors; which over zealous Votes, I am fully perſwaded, theſe ſame members, after due reflection perceiving the fatal conſequences inevitably conſequential to ſuch proceedings, would have recalled, had they ſate longer, or will at their next Seſſions recall them, as being wholly repugnant not only to their Sworn Allegiance and Fidelity, but alſo to Gods revealed will.</p>
            <p>But as to this, time will beſt diſcover the reality of all their intentions; and therefore I leave it to your Majeſties further conſideration, humbly ſubmitting what I have ſaid hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to your moſt Excellent Majeſty, and to your moſt Honourable Privy Council; by whom, I hope, theſe my Reaſons and Arguments ſhall be interpreted with that candour and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, wherewith I here preſent them unto your moſt Excellent Majeſty. And ſo begging of the Almighty to direct your Sacred Majeſty in what is moſt advantageous to the Glory of God, and to the Spirritual and temporal welfare of your Loyal Subjects, I conclude this laſt of <hi>June,</hi> with my everlaſting Prayer, <q>Vivat &amp; Regnet in aeternum &amp; ultra <hi>Carolus</hi> Secundus, nemini Secundus.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101415:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
